<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[LindaKat's Tech Blog]]></title><description><![CDATA[LindaKat's Tech Blog]]></description><link>https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 22:53:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title><![CDATA[Hello, World!]]></title><description><![CDATA[## Welcome to my new blog!

This project got started because I wanted to start writing more tech-related posts. Twitter doesn't give me enough characters, and my other sites just didn't feel quite right. I'd been wanting to dip my toes into learning some actual frameworks, and since I had a long weekend - I decided to do some quick research and see what sounded good!

I knew I wanted to learn Vue when I was ready, so I focused on that pretty quickly. And I knew I wanted something I could host on Netlify, since it's done well for me so far, and I could do it for free - so that meant whatever CMS I was going to use had to be online and likely server-less. I pretty quickly found Netlify CMS, and decided to give Gridsome a try. I hear so much about Gatsby, and Gridsome is meant to be very similar, just written around Vue. Alright - frameworks picked!

I still know next to NOTHING about either of them (and now I've got GraphQL in the mix as well, as the database language), but I was able to figure out enough to get some basic styling done, and get all the details of the posts I wanted visible to show up. It took a lot of trial and error, but somehow I've managed it! There's still a lot to learn, but I've still got improvements I want to make, so I'll be digging in every so often to improve things around here.

For now - what can you expect to find here? I intend to write about a few things: 

* 100 Days of Code logs - more detailed than what I can write on Twitter
* Learning guides - how I got through difficult challenges
* Miscellaneous struggles and successes related to learning to code & job hunting

So - welcome along on the journey! I'll write a bit more about the challenges I've faced so far getting this blog set up soon, and the 100 Days posts should start tomorrow. For now - have a great night, and I'll see ya'll again soon!
]]></description><link>https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/hello-world</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/hello-world</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[behindTheScenes]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2019 05:50:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[100 Days of Code - R2D17]]></title><description><![CDATA[Today was all about getting started with testing Node! Specifically, we're going to be testing the task manager app we've been creating as part of [a Udemy course on learning Nodejs](https://www.udemy.com/the-complete-nodejs-developer-course-2/).

Tonight, all I really got through was installing our testing suite (we're using Jest), and then writing a few simple tests not related to our project, to start to get a feel for how it works.

I'm actually rather excited about this section - I've known for awhile that testing (in particular automatic testing) is an important thing to do. However, I've never really taken the time to learn how to do this yet, or pick a framework for it. One of the many benefits of taking a course - decisions are made for you! :) So far, it seems fairly easy to use! It'll be interesting to get into the next few videos and see how we can actually apply it towards the API we wrote for our project. 

I'm so used to taking courses on front-end projects, that it's a little odd to me that this time around, for this task manager project, we wrote an API that doesn't have a front-end, instead of writing either the front-end only, or both parts together! So far, I think I've been doing decently with Node. It helps that it's so heavily JS based, which is the main language I've focused my learning on. But it's thrown me many times when trying to write Node on my own, deciphering what works for Node and not the browser and vice versa. So I think it's helping a bit that this course is focused so much on just the Node section. A previous project (there's 4 total in the course) had us set up a little bit of a front end, but it was very simple, with just HTML and CSS, so no real confusion. Here's to hoping this is helping cement some of the differences in my brain!
]]></description><link>https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/100-days-of-code-r2d17</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/100-days-of-code-r2d17</guid><category><![CDATA[100DaysOfCode]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 05:38:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Inside My Head Right Now]]></title><description><![CDATA[**I'm gonna be real with you - I've been struggling the past few days.** 

I'm learning to code as a second career. So far in my life, I've only worked as retail associates, customer service roles, or admin assistant spots. Nothing code-specific yet. 

I'm completely self-directed when it comes to coding - no college (for CS, anyways - I did go for music), no boot camps, no mentors. Just me, stumbling onto interesting courses and diving in. I definitely feel like a newb, but I also think I'm vaguely getting the hang of things. 

Last year, I was given the chance to complete a Udacity nano-degree on a Google scholarship, and went through the mobile web track. It was challenging, and interesting, and I felt really accomplished when I completed the course. I chatted and met up with my first developer buddies. I learned things I hadn't come across yet. It promised that we'd have a mentor through the course, and that there would be career help afterwards. 

Well, the mentor thing fell through pretty early on, and the career help was mostly little online courses on writing your resume and polishing your GitHub profile. Which were not completely unhelpful, but also didn't really feel like the guidance I thought I was going to get. None of it was personal. That's okay - that could be my misunderstanding. It would be an ultra amazing thing to have personalized coaching and help for so many students.

The thing is - I'm very ready to move forward with the "getting a job" thing. I want to be working as a developer. There's still a ridiculous amount for me to learn, but I honestly think I've got enough of a handle on things to start being of some benefit to a team. I know how to solve my own issues; I can ask for help when I need it; I'm a bit slow at writing code but I can pretty consistently get it done; I'm open to learning from everyone around me, and I want to dive in and get better and be around other developers on a daily basis. 

But man.....the job search is **ROUGH**. I don't feel like I qualify for 95% of the postings I find. And while yes, I think there is merit to applying for things you don't fully qualify for....when the entire posting reads like a foreign language, it's pretty clear that you wouldn't really have a chance. I don't want something that feels too easy, but I don't want to be drowning, either. 

I haven't been applying to a ton of jobs, but I have applied to some that I felt I could get a good handle on and do well at. Only two so far (out of 10 or so) have said anything back to me personally, and both were rejections. The most recent one was last week, when I'd sent a follow up email to check on it. 

It's never personal, the job rejection. Places will get multiple applications, and they don't actually know me. Still - it hit me hard, and I'm honestly still reeling a bit from it. I'm wondering if programming is actually a field I could fit into. I'm feeling like I still have years to go before I'll be "ready" enough to actually stand a chance. And unfortunately, personal situations in my life are such that I really need to be able to move relatively soon. My current job doesn't pay enough for me to move anywhere, and is a constant source of stress and unhappiness on top of that. So the need to find a new job is very real, and relatively time sensitive.

And the thought of applying for other customer service or office assistant positions....it makes me want to cry. I don't know that my soul can handle many more of those positions. It feels like surrender, like failure, like all I'm good for is a pleasant face and surface level work. 

Don't get me wrong - dealing with customers and running offices is tough work, and requires a lot more skill than most people realize. Still - I'm very ready to be done with that kind of life. And yet, very likely not ready for something more, something new. 

Or maybe I am, and I just don't have my head on straight right now. 

I have so many ideas for things I want to build, and ways I might be able to reword my resume and portfolio site to really start to showcase the best traits I have. It's just that so little of it is code, which seems like the main thing a company will want to see from me to hire me. It's so difficult to prove you're worth the risk, when you don't have any professional experience yet. (Yes, that old Catch 22.)

I have hope, too. Not far under the surface, I've got the determination and perseverance to get back to the search and find more positions that seem possible. I've got the desire to build cool, helpful things; to keep learning and improving; to keep moving forward. My future isn't over; my path isn't a dead end. It just feels like it at this moment, while I'm feeling lost and without direction. A path will show itself soon, I'm sure of it.

Until then...well, it's time to focus on the coding part of all of this a bit more, and try to distract myself from these down feelings. Making progress in learning and projects will inevitably help me feel better, which in turn will give me the brain space I need to make tweaks to my game plan and get back out there.
]]></description><link>https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/inside-my-head-right-now</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/inside-my-head-right-now</guid><category><![CDATA[jobSearch]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 01:14:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[100 Days of Code - R2D18 & 19]]></title><description><![CDATA[I've uncovered two new things about Gridsome this week!

First - it's not going to tell you when something's failing on it's own (Vue fails silently). 

Second - how to change the first thing.

So - the past two days, I've been struggling to figure out why I couldn't run the development command on my blog code, which is set up using Gridsome. It made no sense to me. The last time I'd used it, it had worked! But now, when I'd run the develop command, it would get about 43% of the way through building everything....and just freeze. Often on a different file name, so it didn't seem to be related to any of the specific files it listed when it froze. 

I deleted the .cache folder, as it suggested in the docs, as well as uninstalling and reinstalling the node modules. No change. I tried an older version of Gridsome, in case a new change had caused it. Nothing. I tried it on my desktop (since I'd noticed the problem on my laptop), which is where I'd last run it successfully. Same problem. 

Wtf? 

So I broke down, found the Gridsome Discord group, and asked my question in the help channel. And blissfully, a user came to my rescue! They had a screenshot of the error message they were getting (which I'd never seen), which showed the file that was causing all the trouble.

When I'd last worked on my blog, I'd mostly commented out a page that wasn't working right (I wanted to keep the code so I could keep working on it, but it wasn't working on it's own). I didn't realize it, but I didn't actually run the develop command after I did that. It built just fine, so I didn't think anything of it. But the way I'd commented it out, I had left the template tag open (commenting out the closing tag), which it apparently hated. I would too! ðŸ˜ 

So I moved the closing comment tag up so that the template tag closed, and learned that a template also has to have at least one element in it. So I moved the comment tags again and just left a (seemingly) blank layout element in it - and miraculously, the develop command worked again!

So. Dang. **Thankful!** I'm decent enough with trouble shooting, but with a framework I'm not familiar with, that uses a JavaScript framework I'm not familiar with, and with no obvious error message....I was so lost. So glad I found the Discord group and got a response! 

<hr>

So the next thing was to learn how the heck I get Vue to show me an error message when something goes wrong, so I can have a better shot at fixing it on my own! The Gridsome docs, in the trouble shooting section, mention a line of code to inject to show errors instead of it failing quietly....but no mention about _where_ that codes goes. 

Luckily for me, I was able to figure this one out pretty quickly! I did this by starting to click on the Gridsome config pages in my project until I found one that looked promising, then looked up the docs for that page's API. lol ðŸ˜‰ And lo and behold, I found a command that looked awfully familiar!

So, in the gridsome.server.js folder, inside the module.exports function, I wrote this line of code: 

``` js
api.chainWebpack(config => { config.mode('development') });
```

After saving and running the develop command again, everything still works! And when I stopped the server, moved one of my comment tags in the problem file from before, and tried to run develop again, I got the error message when it failed to build! 

So now, should I have future errors in my files, I'll be able to actually see the error messages, which will help **A LOT** in trouble shooting! ðŸ™Œ Hooray for learning new things!
]]></description><link>https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/100-days-of-code-r2d18-19</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/100-days-of-code-r2d18-19</guid><category><![CDATA[Gridsome]]></category><category><![CDATA[100DaysOfCode]]></category><category><![CDATA[learning]]></category><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 02:51:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[100DaysOfCode R2D27 - Rockin' (Web)Sockets!]]></title><description><![CDATA[I started the last project in my [Node course](https://www.udemy.com/the-complete-nodejs-developer-course-2/) - a chat app! I did the groundwork videos yesterday - getting libraries installed and new files/directories set up.

Tonight, I started getting into the actual code. For this project, the main library we're using is [Socket.io](socket.io), which has been really cool so far! It's got me learning a little bit about web sockets, which is a term I've heard before but haven't really paid attention to.

To my understanding - web sockets are an upgrade to HTTP request/response patterns. They create a connection between a server and a client (or multiple clients!), and keep that connection open so that both sides can send data to each other even faster than you're able to with standard requests. I don't fully understand **HOW** it does this - just that it does.

Socket.io builds on top of this, providing some nice API magic to make it even easier to work with server/client connections. What's really been cool to me is that it's centered around sending (emitting) custom events - so you can name your events anything you want! And then you can send along whatever data you want with it, and just set the other side to listen for that custom event. (It does have a few built ins as well, like connection and disconnect.)

Let me share a simple example we worked on to play around with this. This will show us a basic counter value - then once a button is clicked, it will update the value and show us the new value.

We started with an index.js file (our server file), which is running an Express app. (The io word you see is the variable that's set to our Express server, which socket.io is controlling.) In this file, we set up a variable for a counter, and then when a new client-side connection comes in, we send (emit) a custom named event, and the current value of our count variable.

```js
let count = 0;
```

```js
io.on('connection', (socket) => {   socket.emit('countUpdated', count); })
```

The _socket.emit_ phrase is the key - that's what sends the data off to our client / browser side of things.

On our client, we set up a listener function that listens for the custom event name we just created. When it detects that event being sent, it grabs the data that was sent along with it, and does something with it (in this example, just logs it to the console). (I should note - socket, in this instance, is also a variable defined in our file, which accesses the server we've got running.)

```js
socket.on('countUpdated', (count) => {   console.log('The count has been updated!', count) })
```

So now, when we first connect, our server is calling an event and sending the initial value of count, and our client is picking that event up and logging the value to the console.

Then, if we click a button (which is set up in an html file) on the client side of things, we want to increase the value of count. So we grab the button click event in our client file, and fire off an event to our server, to signify the button was clicked. Again, the name of our event is custom - it could be called whatever! It just has to match on both sides.

```js
document.querySelector('#btnIncrease')  .addEventListener('click', () => {    socket.emit('increment') })
```

Once our server detects this event, we then want to increase the value of count, and send that first event back with the new count value. (This little call takes place inside the `io.on('connection')` call we did earlier.)

```js
socket.on('increment', () => { count++; io.emit('countUpdated', count) })
```

And that's it! Now when we first open the browser to our site, we get a message with the initial count value. And each time we click the button on the page, our client side detects the button click, sends an event to our server, adds 1 to the counter, and the server sends the new value back to the client!

You might have noticed that sometimes I used `socket.emit`, and sometimes `io.emit`. There's 3 basic ideas / use cases that were introduced in the course (so far):

* **socket.emit** - The socket keyword ties to a specific client, so it'll send events only to that particular client.
* **io.emit** - Using the io keyword will send the events to all active, connected clients
* **socket.broadcast.emit** - This isn't in the examples above, but this will send an event to all connected clients **EXCEPT** the specific client you're in (we use this in the course for when a user logs in or out - you want others to see that a new user has joined or left, but you yourself don't need to see when you joined a chat!)

It's been really fun tonight, building out the core functionality for our app. It takes so little code to send and receive information on both ends of the app! It's boggling my mind. ðŸ¤¯ I'm excited to get back to it, and keep working on this project! I already have ideas for how I'd like to use this information. ðŸ˜Š
]]></description><link>https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/100daysofcode-r2d27-rockin-web-sockets</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/100daysofcode-r2d27-rockin-web-sockets</guid><category><![CDATA[100DaysOfCode]]></category><category><![CDATA[nodeCourse]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 05:29:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stamp Inventory Refactor - part 1!]]></title><description><![CDATA[As the title suggests - tonight was spent making some reasonable progress towards updating my stamp inventory site!

A little background on this - I currently work for a print shop, and am the only person who makes self-inking stamps. A few years ago, when I first started learning to code, I decided I wanted to make a little site that could help me keep track of how many of each size stamp I have left in inventory, so it would be a bit easier to see when I needed to reorder things. 

At the time, I had taken a few online courses on spreadsheets and SQL, and felt like I might be able to make something that would work well. After a few failed attempts, all I was left with was frustration and a broken site. 

Finally, I managed to figure out how to hook my site up to a Google spreadsheet, and had a real working site! I was so stoked. It took a lot of hair pulling and it wasn't the absolute best, but it worked and updated properly and I showed it off to everyone I could. 

***

Fast forward a few years. I want to make stylistic changes to it, but remember the frustration and haven't touched the Google sheets API since the first time I made this work. I've finished a few courses that used MongoDB. I need new projects on my portfolio to help with the job search. 

And so, the decision to refactor my site was made!

I've been slowly attempting to work on this off and on for a few weeks - I was able to dismantle all of the jQuery and Google sheets things I wasn't going to need, and through following some FreeCodeCamp material (and my memory of my other courses) got the basics of the Express server in place. But I hadn't really made much progress on actually putting in the database and getting the site to talk to it. 

Well, tonight I finally really got down to it, and made some progress! I fleshed out the Express server part a bit, got my MongoDB cluster set up on Atlas and the connection string saved in my project, and cleaned up the last bit of the file structure. Doesn't feel like much to spell it out, but it's more direct progress than I've made since I started working on it again, so I'll take it!

Mind you, I can't get it started on my local testing site yet. ðŸ˜œ But I'm fairly certain I can get that working tomorrow (ðŸ¤ž). I just ran out of time tonight, since I was working in the local library and they were about to close. 

***

What I still can't decide on, is how I want to do my schemas. 

We carry 5 different sizes of stamps, and for each size I keep track of the die box (the actual stamp part), and the mount (the holder for the die box). I'm also loosely keeping track of the 3 ink colors, and the gloves and 2 sheets we use to actually print the design and flash it onto the stamp. 

Do I want to keep each individual piece as it's own type, that just has a name and a quantity? This seems like it might be the best option. However, I do want to have some check boxes for if some of the accessory parts are used, and would need a way to grab the current value for those and decrease them by the same amount (or automatically decrease it by 1 or 2, for the gloves and print sheets). Seems like I should be able to do that....but I'm not sure how difficult it will turn out to be. 

I could also count each size as it's own thing, with a value for the die box and a value for the mount. This might make it easier to associate those 2 parts together, since more often than not they'll be used in the same quantity. But for some customers, we make new die boxes but reuse the mounts, so it won't always be equal in usage. And I still want a check box for the print sheets. 

Though I could maybe work in a double tap / hold functionality to the space where I show those quantities, and change them that way....wouldn't be quite as nice as changing it at the same time as the stamp option, but we do have times where people order more than one size so it wouldn't be that big of a deal to change each item separately. That make actually work really nicely, since I'm currently using a form to mark each item so anything will be better than that. 

I would also really like a nicer way to keep track of the inks....still trying to decide on the best way to do that. It's basically eye balled each time a die box gets filled, so it's not an exact, pre-filled amount that goes into each one. Which makes keeping track of how much is used a bit more difficult. 

Clearly I have some more thinking to do! First task is to get it so I can actually view the site and access the database at all. Then I can make a decision on the schema so I can start putting actual data into it! ðŸ˜Š
]]></description><link>https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/stamp-inventory-refactor-part-1</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/stamp-inventory-refactor-part-1</guid><category><![CDATA[stampInventory]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 06:30:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[AoC (Advent of Code) - 2019 Day 1!]]></title><description><![CDATA[Advent of Code is finally here, and I'm so excited!! This is such a fun code challenge, and I was really bummed when I couldn't keep up with it last year, so I'm determined to stay on it this year and follow through until the end!

<details>
<summary>**Spoilers will follow from here on out** - avoid until you've solved the problems if you want! Click the arrow to view.</summary>

This year is set in space! I think it'll be really fun to see how the story unfolds.
Day 1, thankfully, felt pretty good! 

I was able to refresh on how to use the array methods `map` and `reduce`, along with some recursion practice, which was good! One of the rare days where I felt like I knew what I was doing, which is always nice. 

I'm including these in today's post, but might start to exclude the first few lines in future posts. Basically, each day will start with reading in the input file, and parsing it as an array of either strings or numbers, or otherwise setting it up to be read. Think that will be a given once enough of these posts are done!

```javascript
// Read in the input file, get it into an array format, & store the test input as well
const fs = require('fs');

const data = fs.readFileSync('../2019 Solutions/inputs/day01input.txt').toString();

const input = data.split('\r\n').map(Number);

const testInput = [14, 1969, 100756];

// The formula needed to calculate the required amount of fuel - mass / 3, round down, -2
function formula(mass) {
  return Math.floor(mass / 3) - 2;
}

// Part 1 - perform this formula on each input value, then add all of those values together
const fuelOfMass = input.map((curr) => {
  return formula(curr);
});

const totalFuel = fuelOfMass.reduce((acc, curr) => {
  return acc + curr;
}, 0);

console.log(`Part 1: ${totalFuel}`);

// Part 2 - turns out, we need to process each input value through the formula until the number is as low as it can get and still be above 0, then add all of a single input's values together

const totalFuelOfMass = input.map((curr) => {
  let value = curr;
  let accumulator = [];

  do {
    value = formula(value);
    if (value > 0) {
      accumulator.push(value);
    }
  } while (value > 0);
  
  return accumulator.reduce((acc, curr) => {
    return acc + curr;
  }, 0);
});

// then, we take all of the combined values and add those together
const newTotalFuel = totalFuelOfMass.reduce((acc, curr) => {
  return acc + curr;
}, 0);

console.log(`Part 2: ${newTotalFuel}`);
```

If you'd like to read the full breakdown for what today's puzzle required, you can check it out [on the main site](https://adventofcode.com/2019/day/1). You should be able to see it, even if you're not signed in. 

</details>

Part of this year's new changes on the official subreddit is a poem contest! Each day, you can submit a poem about the challenge itself, the creator, or general programming, and every few days they'll reward some people with reddit points and make a collection of their favorites for an end-of-year collection. I love poetry, so couldn't resist getting in on the fun for at least one day! Enjoy!

> Adventure awaits!
>
> Discover the cosmos
>
> Venture into the unknown
>
> Earn fifty stars to save Christmas!
>
> No one goes alone, however
>
> There's friendly folks to help
>
> Overly dramatic situations await
>
> Find Santa and bring him home!
>
> Come code with us!
>
> Outer space is calling
>
> Don't be afraid
>
> Elves will guide the way!
]]></description><link>https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/aoc-advent-of-code-2019-day-1</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/aoc-advent-of-code-2019-day-1</guid><category><![CDATA[AoC]]></category><category><![CDATA[adventOfCode]]></category><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 07:24:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Do I Own This? A New Project!]]></title><description><![CDATA[I have this very first world problem. 

You see, I love nail polish. Can't get enough. And so, most times when I'm at the store, I browse through the polish to see if anything is speaking to me. 

The problem is, I often see colors that I like - but I have so many at home, that I can't remember the names of them all! And so every time, without fail, I wonder - "Do I own this"? 

I do this with shirts, too - I'm a fan of basic, solid colors of shirts, but can never remember which colors I already have when I'm out at the store. I try to remember to take a picture of my closet before I leave, but almost always forget, or eventually lose the photo or don't update it once I buy new things.

So! I want to make an app that can help me quickly & easily check when I'm at the store, and never have to not buy something because I can't remember if I already own it or not. 

I have a few ideas on this, but I'm still uncertain on how I want to do things. So this is a bit of a brainstorming session, in the hopes that I either make some decisions and/or can get some advice. ðŸ˜Š

<hr>

## **UI Factors**

For the main page, I want to keep it simple. I'm envisioning a nice, clean grid, that just shows color swatches of each color. Rounded corners, probably, because I love rounded corners and think it looks a bit more polished that way. (HA! What a punny joke. Sorry, I couldn't resist.)

I'll need to have a search/filter bar somewhere, so that I can view just a particular shade or brand if desired. I can't decide if I want this to always be visible, or if it should be behind a little menu option? I'm leaning towards always visible as I think that's both more accessible & faster - but I can't see it in my mind's eye. I want the color grid to be the most obvious, visible thing, but I think a filter bar should be on the top if it's going to be visible all the time. Maybe I can make a little side tray that comes in and out when needed? I don't know. Both would look nice, but I can't see this part in my mind yet. 

Then I want a way, when a particular color is clicked, to show it's name, brand, color group, etc. Normally when I'm at the store, I'm looking at a particular brand at a time, so if I can filter my view to just that brand it's often easy to get an idea of if I've got a particular color or not. Then I can click on it to verify before I write it off. Or I can filter by color group, so I can decide if I've already got enough purple shades (I do) or if the shade that's calling to me is missing from my group. I don't think the color's name or brand needs to be visible on the main view, but it needs to be easily accessible for verification purposes. Hmmm...or maybe I can fit the color name underneath each swatch? I don't know, some of these names are weird and long and I don't know that they'll fit nicely. 

Lastly, I'll need a way to add new colors, so I can keep my collection updated. This can definitely be stowed away in a menu, or in a small button somewhere. A simple form for filling in the information will work, then it'll need a way to upload a picture. I'll have to think on the pictures, as I'll want them to stay as uniform as possible, but that will really be up to the person taking the pictures (me). 

<hr>

## **Back-end Factors**

This is where I'm struggling the most. I'll definitely need a database to store all of this data. But I'm trying to think now about how it might be used in the future - and I think it's possible, if I can get the UI stuff down, that others might want to use this as well. So I want to consider writing this in a way that it can be hosted somewhere, and a database can be kept up. Which is not something I've really had to deal with on any projects I've done so far. 

Everything so far has just been for me, so it's been hosted on Heroku or a Github page. And if I've needed a database I've used a MongoDB free cluster and just tinkered around, or I've used a JSON file. Which, I could probably set it up to use a JSON file - I know it's easy and fast to pull the data from, & I'm sure I could work out how to write the data to it so that it stays clean and organized. It would be personal for each person who uses it, which (since I don't intend to add any shared items) would be fine, but then each person would have to store the site somewhere on their own.  

However, it feels like I should use a legit database for this, where each person can just have their own collection stored. Plus, more real world practice for me! But I don't have much real experience with actual databases, in a production sense. I don't have the funds to pay for a lot of data storage (on the off chance this somehow turns out amazing and goes viral), but I don't think there's much that's really free in terms of data storage or server options. So I'm not really sure where to go with this. 

It might honestly be worth it to only worry about myself for now, and host it on Heroku with either a JSON file or a MongoDB cluster. For my own data, it'll be free, which is a big concern at the moment. But I would like to consider releasing this for the public in the future, if I can get this really finished. So I want to think about how I can set it up so that, even if I do it just for me for now, it'll be relatively easy to be able to expand the hosting. I don't want to completely rewrite anything if I can help it!

I'm also concerned, if I'm able to push it live to others, about it responsibly using data & phone storage - since mobile will be a main use case. So I'll have to look into that, as well. This, along with collections potentially being large, is a main factor that keeps me from considering something like local storage for the database. Plus, the data will need to persist so someone's collection doesn't just disappear, and I don't think local storage is the best option for that.

<hr>

Alright, so the idea is out there! Now to actually build the dang thing. ðŸ˜Ž

If anyone has any suggestions, please reach out & let me know! Especially if you've got thoughts on the back-end part of this, which is what's holding me back the most! It's entirely possible I'm way overthinking this, and should just focus on building for me and getting a working version up before I worry too much about the world at large. But I'd love to hear your thoughts on anything I've mentioned here! I intend to write about my process as I go along, so this is just the beginning. ðŸ’…
]]></description><link>https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/do-i-own-this-a-new-project</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/do-i-own-this-a-new-project</guid><category><![CDATA[doIOwnThis]]></category><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2020 04:45:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hello World - I'm Learning Vue!]]></title><description><![CDATA[
I've been wanting to learn a framework for a little while now, & it was recently advised to me that it would be smart to do job-wise. So I've finally decided to buckle down & choose one, & decided on Vue!

My reasoning - it's open source based; people I respect in the field rave about it & work on it; it's growing quickly; & it seemed to be a bit of a middle ground between React & Angular. Plus, I'm using a framework based on it for my personal blog already!

So I'm using this post as a basic, beginner's cheat sheet for examples of how to do things in Vue. This will be pretty simplified, and may not use the most accurate terminology - it will be more how my brain sees & thinks of it. I'm basing this off of the extremely well done Vue Mastery [Intro to Vue](https://www.vuemastery.com/courses/intro-to-vue-js) course - it's free and has videos, text, and challenges! Basically everything I write here is simply a retelling of it to help solidify my understanding - if anything doesn't make sense here, I highly recommend you check out their course, as it's explained way better than I can do!

So let's begin!

----

## The Vue Instance

Any time you'd like Vue to control a part of the DOM in a project, you'll create a new instance of Vue. Basically, this is a structured grouping of information needed for a piece of your site.

You declare the instance in your JS file, which will look something like this:

```js
var app = new Vue({
Â el: '#app',  
Â data: {
Â Â product: 'Socks',
Â Â description: 'A pair of warm, fuzzy socks'
Â }
})
```

Anytime you're starting a new instance, you use the keyword new. Think of the Vue instance as a big object container, with lots of pieces of data (since that's essentially what you're doing - Vue holds a big options object, with all sorts of things). Here, we've got an "el", which stands for element - this is the ID you're trying to target in your HTML, the element this instance is going to be able to interact with. Then you can add some data, with whatever you'd like inside it. For these examples, it's building out a website to sell socks, so we've got a product & description listed.

Then in your HTML file, you can access the data from your Vue instance with double braces around the key word. This is a JS expression used in HTML - it's pretty neat! And since this is a JS expression, you can also use this to tie different pieces of data together & create new values.

```html
<div id="app">
Â <div class="product-info">
Â Â <h1>{{ product }}</h1>
Â Â <p>{{ "Description: " + description }}</p>
Â </div>
</div>
```

----

### Two quick side notes:

First - It's really easy to start using Vue - you can plug it into your projects with a script tag, like you would your style sheet or your regular JS files! (There's also a CLI tool to use it, but I haven't dug into that yet.)

Second - Vue is a reactive framework, which means that when you change a value in your Vue instance, anywhere it's referenced in your HTML will be updated automatically. This is almost like real magic, honestly. It's so cool.

----

## Data / Attribute Binding

We can also directly bind data to an attribute in Vue. Unlike the expressions we just talked about (which can be used on any sort of attribute we want, within our element attached to the Vue instance), this will be a piece of data that's directly tied to a specific HTML attribute.

Say this is our updated JS file:

```js
var app = new Vue({
Â el: '#app',
Â data: {
Â Â product: 'Socks',
Â Â image: 'https://www.vuemastery.com/images/challenges/vmSocks-green-onWhite.jpg',
Â Â link: 'http://www.vuemastery.com'
Â }
})
```

We've added two new keys to our data object - an image & a link.

To bind this to a specific attribute, it will look like this in our HTML:

```html
<div class="product-image">
Â <img v-bind:src="image" />
</div>
```

You'll use the `v-bind:` to show Vue you want to bind some data here, then you list which attribute you're binding to - in this case, the `src` attribute. Then, where you'd otherwise write in the source link, you write the key from your data object instead.

This doesn't just have to be for links - you can use it with text as well, or really any attribute where you want the data to be able to automatically stay updated.

Since this is a pretty common thing, there's also a short hand way to write this, which is just the colon:

```html
<div class="product-info">
Â <h1>{{ product }}</h1>
Â <a :href="link">Intro to Vue Course</a>
</div>
```

So it almost looks just like it normally would, only the href has a `:` in front of it, and instead of a url inside the quotes, we have the key from our data object.

----

One of the big reasons to use JS on your website is the ability to perform different actions based on logic. Typically, these work out as conditional logic (if/else) and looping over data (for loops especially). Good news - Vue makes this really easy!

----

## Conditional Rendering

Say we add a data field to our instance, to check if our socks are in stock or not. We can do that pretty easily!

In our JS file, we'll add an inStock key to our data section:

```js
var app = new Vue({
Â el: '#app',
Â data: {
Â Â product: 'Socks',
Â Â image: 'https://www.vuemastery.com/images/challenges/vmSocks-green-onWhite.jpg',
Â Â link: 'http://www.vuemastery.com',
  inStock: true
Â }
})
```

Then, in our HTML, we can write two different options - one we want to show if they are available, and one to show when they're sold out.

```html
<p v-if="inStock">In Stock</p>
<p v-else>Out of Stock</p>
```

Pretty simple, right? It works on expressions too, not just truthy values, and there's even an `else if` option if we need more complex logic:

```html
<p v-if="inventory > 10">Available</p>
<p v-else-if="inventory <= 10 && inventory > 0">Almost sold out!</p>
<p v-else>Out of Stock</p>
```

This works great for things that will be displayed conditionally whenever the page loads, or if something needs to update once or twice - but if you've got something that will need to toggle frequently, there's another option that's more performant - v-show.

The if/else option actually inserts and/or removes the elements, which could be problematic if something is changing regularly without a fresh page load. With show, the element is always present in the DOM - it just toggles a `display: none` property. This will work much better for something that needs to change multiple times.

```html
<p v-show="inStock">In Stock</p>
```

----

## Looping

Ok, let's say we have some details about our product that we want to be able to list out easily. For loop to the rescue!

In our data object of our Vue instance, we'll have this details array:

```js
var app = new Vue({
Â el: '#app',
Â data: {
Â Â product: 'Socks',
Â Â image: 'https://www.vuemastery.com/images/challenges/vmSocks-green-onWhite.jpg',
Â Â link: 'http://www.vuemastery.com',
  inStock: true,
  details: ["80% cotton", "20% polyester", "machine washable"]
Â }
})
```

We can make that into a list in our HTML like so:

```html
<ul>
  <li v-for="detail in details">{{ detail }}</li>
</ul>
```

This basically works like a `for of` or `for in` loop, where we say "we want each piece in this collection". The name we pick for the piece doesn't really matter - it's an alias for what we want to call each piece of the thing we're looping over. The collection name will matter - that needs to line up with the name of your collection in your data object. Then, in the curly braces, we list what information we want from each piece.

This can work for arrays of objects as well! Say we have two different color variations of our socks - we can make elements that show this as well.

In our data, we'll have a variants array:

```js
var app = new Vue({
Â el: '#app',
Â data: {
Â Â product: 'Socks',
Â Â image: 'https://www.vuemastery.com/images/challenges/vmSocks-green-onWhite.jpg',
Â Â link: 'http://www.vuemastery.com',
  inStock: true,
  details: ["80% cotton", "20% polyester", "machine washable"],
  variants: [
    {
      variantId: 2234,
      variantColor: "green"
    },
    {
      variantId: 2235,
      variantColor: "blue"
    }
  ]
Â }
})
```

In our HTML, we can then loop through each variant, and access the color field.

```html
<div v-for="variant in variants" :key="variant.variantId">
  <p>{{ variant.variantColor }}</p>
</div>
```

You'll see I have a key attribute listed as well - this is recommended with more complex nodes like this, so Vue has an easier time keeping track of each node. Here, it's using the id of each variant, though you could use any unique piece of an object.

----

There's so much more Vue can do - but this post is long enough as it is. If I'm able, I'll do another post for the other sections of the course, but for now, I have more learning to do!

Again, check out the Vue Mastery [Intro to Vue](https://www.vuemastery.com/courses/intro-to-vue-js) course if you have a chance! I've also got a [CodePen Collection of my challenge pens here](https://codepen.io/collection/XqVKjY) if you'd like to see the code at work.

Happy learning!
]]></description><link>https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/learning-vue</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lindakat-blogs.netlify.com/posts/learning-vue</guid><category><![CDATA[vue]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 03:28:56 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>